A Guide to the Papers of the Bantz family (and others) of Frederick, Md. and Winchester, Va., 1740-1910
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Bantz family (and others) of Frederick, Md. and Winchester, Va. 1740-1910
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8884-e
Ca. 650 items (7 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited by Mrs. Mary Beirne K. Nutt on November 12, 1976.
Scope and Content
Collections of the Winchester, Va., and Frederick, Md., family include account books of T. Marion Bantz, Gideon Bantz, John M. Miller, and John Leight, extensive history and genealogy of area families (some relating to German settlements in Maryland and the Crouse family in Adams County, Pa.), correspondence, indentures, and miscellaneous accounts.
Also included are order books, morning reports, and miscellaneous reports of several companies of the First Regiment Michigan Infantry, 1861-1862, and other miscellaneous war papers including material from the U.S Christian Commission.
Of interest is a letter from R. F. Weir, General Hospital, Frederick, Md., 1864 November 21 concerning the lack of Thanksgiving dinner for soldiers.
Other assorted materials include an 1871 War Department weather map, an 1880 recipe book of Julia Ann Derkehart, a loan record book, 1846-1847, of the Frederick-town Branch Bank., clipping scrapbook of the travels of Bishop Thomas Bowman in Europe, 1865 income tax forms, and 1835 astronomical maps. Also included is copy of a 1794 surveyor's plat of Winchester, Va., and various advertisements.
Contents List
- Series I: Family Papers
  - Miscellaneous letters, notes, pieces in German 1740-1806, 17 items (Box 1)
    Mostly to Philip Hoover (Phillippe Huber, Hoober); also two letters in English
  - Indentures 1777-1840; 1876, 14 items (Box 1)
  - Articles of Agreement 1780-1840, 24 items (Box 1)
  - Two sections of German newspapers 1796, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Letter: A discourse on the Clock; "Dear Friend" from "Gaillard" 1798 Sept. 8, 10 p. (Box 1)
  - "A Method for Gilding" n.d., 1 item (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous accounts, vouchers, of Philip Hoover or Lewis Hartman, Frederick Co., Virginia 1800-1830, ca. 15 items (Box 1)
  - Bills, receipts ca. 1790-1830, ca. 40 items (Box 1)
  - "Mother parden me for not wrighing to you suner..."; Letter, George Bentley to his Mother 1817 Oct. 22, 3 p. (Box 1)
    re: money & legal problems & general tales of woe
  - Miscellaneous plats, surveys, titles to lands, Frederick and Winchester Co. ca. 1820-1860, 7 items (Box 1)
  - Bills, receipts 1830-1870, ca. 30 items (Box 1)
  - Misc. letters 1840-1866, 5 items (Box 1)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts ca. 1840-1860, ca. 50 items (Box 1)
  - Bills, receipts; 15 pamphlets, "Soldiers Series" (homilies), & obviously later date n.d., 22 items (Box 1)
  - Bills, accounts 1870s and after, ca. 50 items (Box 1)
  - Miscellany - photograph, map, and article, "The Use of Soil Surveys," & certificate ca. 1900, 4 items (Box 1)
  - Accounts & statements to the Court 1752 July 27, Aug. 7 (Box 2)
  - Subpoena for John Armstrong from Frederick Co. 1764 Dec. 4, 1 p. (Box 2)
  - Record of the Frederick Co., Md., Court 1767 Aug., 14 p. (torn in half) (Box 2)
  - Account Book n.d., 14 pp. (Box 2)
  - Arithmetic Book n.d., ca. 33 pp. (Box 2)
  - Workbook for Plane Trigonometry and Surveying by Gideon Bantz 1829, ca. 200 pp. (Box 2)
  - Summonses, bills, & receipts ca. 1840-1850, ca. 200 items (Box 2)
  - Memorandum & Account Book 1894, 3 items (Box 2)
  - Acts of Parliament ca. 1661, 18th or 19th century, 6 folders (Box 2)
    Bundles of Acts of Parliament, appearing to be later reprints of the originals. They seem to cover the period of Edward IV (& possibly sooner) to George II.
  - Cookbook of Julia Ada Derkehart 1880 Jan., ca. 200 pp. (Box 3)
  - Notebook originally of a Baltimore Fire Company, now filled with genealogy, mechanics, etc. n.d., ca. 100 pp. (Box 3)
  - Notebook including genealogy, history, mechanics, etc. 1872-1895, ca. 100 pp. (Box 3)
  - Cookbook by Julian Hartman ca. 1830-1831, ca. 150 pp. (Box 3)
  - Scrap-album: Newspaper clippings from religious publications ca. 1878, ca. 30 pp. (Box 3)
  - Account Book of Gideon Bantz's estate 1854-1893, ca. 200 pp. (Box 4)
  - U.S. Christian Commission - Delegate's Notebook belonging to Gideon Bantz 1864-1865, 111 p. (Box 4)
  - Notes on the History of New Jersey, Delaware & Virginia n.d., 2p. ANS (Box 4)
  - Notes on the Estate of Gideon Bantz by John E.R. Wood, auditor 1887-1892, 2 p. ADS (Box 4)
  - Marion Bantz to his Mother 1865 Feb. 2, 2 p. ALS (Box 4)
  - Account book of G. Bantz Jr., for estate of G. Bantz 1854-1864, ca. 200 p. (Box 4)
  - Land sale agreement 1816 Dec. 2, 4p. ADS (Box 4)
  - Account book of T. Marion Bantz 1868-1873, ca. 75 p. (Box 4)
  - Account Book of G. Bantz as guardian to Ne Doll heirs 1855-1865, ca. 100 p. (Box 4)
  - Misc. notes on the Bantz family 1858-1863, ca. 150 p. (Box 4)
  - Account Book of Gideon Bantz 1849-1857, ca. 300 p. (Box 4)
  - Account Book of Gideon Bantz 1862-1901, ca. 200 p. (Box 4)
  - Printed vol.: Loan Record book of the Frederick Town Bank 1846 June 17, 1847 Sept. 29, ca. 200 p. (Box 4)
  - Account Book of T. Marion Bantz, Winchester, Va. 1898 Jan. 1-1905 July 15, ca. 200 pp. (Box 5)
  - Account Book of John M. Miller, Middletown Mills 1852-1859, ca. 250 pp. (Box 5)
  - Report of Through Ticket Sales at (05) Office, Richmond 1875 Dec.-1876 Apr., 296 p., only p.1 used (Box 5)
  - Account Book of John Leight 1837 Sept.-Nov., ca. 300 p. (Box 5)
  - Crouse family history & genealogy, Adams Co., Pennsylvania ca. 1750-ca. 1850, 37 pp. (Box 6)
  - Genalogical information concerning many (German immigrants), families, seeming primarily in Maryland (Frederick) area ca. 1700-1900, 3 items, ca. 250 pp. (Box 6)
  - Lutheran Church Records; Family history, genealogy ca. 1700-1900, ca. 150 pp. (Box 6)
  - Family Records ca. 1750-1870, 5 items (Box 6)
    Item headings as follows: John Ives Hartman; "Old Defender's War 1814"; Eagle, Keller, & Smith families; "Genealogy of Brunners"; "Genealogy of the Sinns"
  - Family history & Genealogy ca. 1740-1860, 10 items, ca. 150 pp. (Box 6)
    Item headings: "Merche nov Markell"; "Black Horse Hotel (Jacob Schmidt)"; "Cigar-maker - green grocer (Kline)"; "Paper-maker - Farmer (John William Birely)"; "Farmer - (Wm Smith)"; "John Lachlan Harding"; "Bantz Family"; "Balthazar Fo[ret]"; "Sinn Family"; "Hugh Fisher, Engineer"; seems to be information relating to German settlements in Maryland.
  - List or indexes [to genealogical records?] ca. 1850s, 2 items, ca. 25 pp.
    booklets in cardboard binding containing lists of names followed by numbers
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Letter, R.F. of the General Hospital in Frederick, Md. to Mrs. G. Bantz 1864 Nov. 21, 1 p. and lettercover (Box 7)
    re inability to provide soldiers with a Thanksgiving meal, due to hospital debts
  - Letter, Gideon Bantz to Messeurs Fisher & Co., St. Louis 1879 Jan. 30, 1 p., draft (Box 7)
    informing them that they have mistaken him for another Bantz in St. Louis and that he owes no debts. On verso: a blank patent form for "improved horse power."
  - Letter, Duttera and Buckley, Tanners and Dealers in leather, hides, etc. of Gettysburg to Ernest Bantz of Frederick 1887 Aug. 1, 2 p. and lettercover (Box 7)
  - Lettter, [T] Marion [Bantz], Winchester, to Ernest Bantz, Frederick City 1887 Aug. 15, 1 p. and lettercover (Box 7)
  - Draft of letter, unfinished and unsigned to Marion [Bantz] n.d., 18__ (Box 7)
    re inventory of property and plans for public sale, an advertisement for a tanner and the health of Ann [?]; composed on a section of an official Morning Attendance Report which bears the signature of J.B. Kennedy and J.E. Songley
  - Court statement of land sale to David Mainhart with note at bottom to "My dear friend" n.d., 2 p. (Box 7)
    On verso draft of letter, unsigned, to "My very kind friend" re burial of Mrs. Towers
- Series III: Miscellaneous Papers
  - Miscellaneous accounts, bills, receipts, vouchers, etc. 1792-1859, 13 items (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous accounts, bills, receipts, vouchers, etc. 1860-1890, 12 items (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1861-1864, 1 p. ANS; ANS (Box 7)
    re government military hospitals including 2 passes admitting Gideon Bantz into hospitals in Alexandria and Frederick; Moses Gunn certifying that E. Griffith Carn is unable to attend fort due to illness; noting the hospitalization of John B. Payne and one card permit explaining rules and regulations in Frederick City, Md.
  - Delegate's reports and printed matter re the U.S. Christian Commission ca. 1861-1864, 9 items (Box 7)
  - Clothing and supply lists and a list of men participating in a raffle of the watch of a wounded comrade 1862 July 18, n.d., 3 items (Box 7)
  - Descriptive list and account of pay and clothing of Private William E. Hyslop, Company "G," First Regiment, Michigan Infantry 1862 Aug. 14, 2 p. (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous attendance records and list of soldiers ca. 1862-1865 (Box 7)
    including notes on number killed and wounded; also reporting forms, leave passes and Treasury Department rules for discharge and bounty
  - Miscellaneous accounts, bills, receipts and notes re tanning trade 1864-1887, 5 items (Box 7)
  - Advertisements, Continental Fire Company, New York, and Perry and Boley's anti-friction pump ca. 1866-1910, 4 items (Box 7)
  - Trial record, Gideon Bantz: Exhibit "A" 1869 Feb. 2, 13 p. (Box 7)
    complaint by Bantz against David H. and Henry W. Taylor re invention and patent of a "new and useful improvement in furnaces for heating steam boilers, etc."
  - Way-Bill, Winchester to Hamilton and return, and one conductor's Way-Bill Eastward bearing note "Henry Bantz married Catharine Smith" 186_ and 1871, Oct. 1-Nov. 22, 4 items (Box 7)
  - Items re death and estate of Elizabeth Ritt, including last will and testament 1876 Apr.-May, 7 items (Box 7)
  - Autograph deed 1878 Dec. 31, 2 p. (Box 7)
    re estate of Ann Maria Bantz signed by J.G. Bantz, executor of last will and testament
  - Pages from The Baltimore Sun News and miscellaneous clippings 1889 Oct. 6, n.d., 4 p. (Box 7)
    re weather, inventions, religious matters, etc., origins unknown
  - Blank checks and insurance notes and membership to Masons 18__, 7 items (Box 7)
  - Notification of Bankruptcy of Arthur P. Baer and Charles E. Savage with list of creditors and amounts owed n.d., 1 item (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous items n.d., 8 items (Box 7)
    including wrappers for stationary, sketches, a card photograph and drawing of George Washington
  - Miscellaneous scraps of paper, mostly blank, some bearing penmanship exercises n.d. (Box 7)
- Series IV: Drawings and Maps
  - Plat of the town of Winchester and the commons 1752 Dec. 10 (Box 7)
  - War Department weather map 1871 May 6 (Box 7)
  - 1-page specifications for bridge over Israel's Creek near Walkersville, and 18-page specifications with text and drawings for additional bridges, drawn up on backs of morning attendance reports n.d., 2 items (Box 7)